{
  "reference_number": "11804",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "This is a critical move to ensure that NZ is an internationally responsible country and it is good for the economy by providing a clear\n direction (that avoids policy lurches)"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "It would be extremely irrational to ignore methane and NOx. Indeed the agricultural sector has been free-riding for far too long."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "If well organised with safeguards and appropriate auditing - some level of trading of carbon units is an extremely efficient way to\n achieve emissions reductions. It also helps build international cooperation in achieving emissions reductions."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes - the situation may change which makes it necessary to bring forward the target to say 2040. Also we need as a country to be\n\n prepared for other contingencies such as a global economic decline or nuclear war etc."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Absolutely - we need continuous steps toward achieving the 2050 goal."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "Yes - the future is so uncertain that governments do need some flexibility"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But just under exceptional circumstances"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Absolutely - plans are critical"
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "All sectors must be considered - including agriculture. Even Department of Conservation since ruminant pests (deer, goats) are both\ndamaging native forests but also to greenhouse gas emissions. There is also a particular need to consider the health co-benefits\n\nthat arise from improving insulation of the housing stock, reducing air pollution from burning coal etc, increasing the level of active\ntransport to work (good for health and lowers emissions), and improving diets (less ruminant meat and dairy products) - is good for\n\nemissions reduction and good for health."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Absolutely - monitoring is critical."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "The NZETS is currently terribly poorly designed. It needs to be substantially fixed or scrapped and replaced with a carbon tax (ideally\n\nas per the design of the British Colombia one - with recycling of the revenue to the community)."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes - some of the revenue from carbon taxes should be used to assist with adaptation. Some of the defence budget should probably\nbe diverted towards this purpose - given that climate change is a threat to the country's security."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Climate change is a huge issue. The NZ Government response over the last few decades has been relatively poor (eg, in contrast to\nScandinavian countries eg, Finland with a carbon tax since 1990). It is completely appropriate that there is a large scale effort to\n\nreduce NZ's emissions. But substantial diplomatic effort should also be directed to explore such issues as NZ being part of a \"Climate\nClub\" where there is carbon credit trading (see publications by Nordhaus etc) - and where tariffs are imposed on countries which are\n\nnot adequately responding to climate change."
    }
  ]
}
